In the previous unit, we talked
about the assembly process and, and
logic in general, and
about writing assemblers in general.
And in this unit, we will start
the journey of actually building
an assembler, an assembler that works and
that can translate programs from symbolic
hack code into binary Hack code.
So here is the overall
picture in a nutshell.
We are given a source program written
in symbolic Hack language and
we have to translate it into an equivalent
program written in binary code.
So if you were the person who's supposed
to write to develop such an assembler,
how would you go about it?
And what, what is the knowledge
that you have to know in order to
develop such a general purpose translator?
Because bear in mind, we have to be able
to translate any program written in Hack
symbolic code, not just the subset
of programs but any given program.
Well, this is, in general,
it's a translation challenge, right?
You have to translate from one language,
from the source language,
to the target language.
And in order to do this, you have to
know the grammar of both languages.
You have to know the syntax rules.
For example, if you want to translate
from French to Spanish, you have to know
the grammatical rules of French in
order to take the source sentence and
decompose it or
parse it into its lingual elements.
Then you observe or
you inspect these elements.
You figure out what is
the semantics of this sentence, and
then you re-express
the semantics in Spanish.
And in order to do this, you have to
know the rules of the game in Spanish.
You have to be able to synthesize a target
sentence written in the target language.
And that's exactly what we do here.
However, when we write translators for
programming languages,
the task is supremely easier because
programming languages are supremely
simpler than human spoken languages or
natural languages.
And in particular, machine languages
are are very simple, and therefore
the translation task is going to be less
formidable as it may seem at the outset.
All right, so what do we have
to know about the Hack language?
Well, the Hack language
consists of A-instructions,
C-instructions, and symbols.
So let us explore every one of
these categories very briefly.
The A-instruction comes up
in in its symbolic syntax.
And here is the equivalent binary syntax.
And if you want to
translate one to the other,
I think it doesn't take too much
imagination to figure out how to do it.
And in any rate, we are going to
say it explicitly down the road.
The C-instruction in a very similar
fashion, has a symbolic syntax and
a binary syntax.
And there's a set of tables that describe
the mapping between the former and
the, the latter.
And finally the Hack
language features symbols.
You know, the programmer is invited
to use some pre-defined symbols.
And also, the programmer is invited
to invent symbols of his or
her own using the label
declaration statement and
eth statements or A-instructions that
are designed to declare and use variables.
So this, basically, you know,
this is a complete description
of the Hack machine language and
given this description,
you should be able to develop
the desired assembler.
So given that we have a program
in which all these things
that I mentioned before come to play in a,
in a vivid example.
What exactly do we have here, you know,
in terms of general constructs?
Well, first of all, we have white space.
We haven't mentioned white space in the
language specification, we should have.
But the white space is almost the same in
every language that you can think about.
You are welcome to introduce
empty lines and comments and
in the Hack language, a comment is
anything that begins with two slashes.
So we have to know how to
deal with white space.
And then we have a sequence of
A-instructions and C-instructions
that we have to translate, and finally,
we have to deal with the symbols.
Symbols come to play either in
label declaration commands or
in references in the context
of A-instructions.
So, to make a long story short, if you
want to write an assembler, you have to
know how to deal with white space,
with instructions, and with symbols.
Let me say a few words about symbols
before we before we go along.
I've used red ink in what you see here in
order to highlight all the symbols that
appear in this program and it's, as you
can see, there are quite a few of them.
And that's quite characteristic to
symbolic machine language programs.
They have numerous symbols in them.
So the question is,
how do we deal with these symbols?
Well you know, the answer is that
in many cases in life when you face
a big mountain in front of your
track well, in some cases,
you know, the best way to deal with this
mountain Is simply to, to bypass it.
And that's exactly what I'm
going to do with the symbols.
I'm going to deal with them later.
And by the way, if we are lucky,
as we bypass this mountain,
we may gain some ground and
then summiting the mountain
may be easier from the other side
than from the original side.
And indeed, you will see that when we'll
introduce symbols later on in the process,
it will be much easier to to morph them,
so to speak, into our assembler solution.
All right, so symbols later and
with that in mind,
I now have to deal only with
programs that have no symbols.
And the assembler that I have
to write is much simpler.
It's an assembler that deals with
symbol-less symbolic Hack programs.
So the challenge that remain is to deal
with white space and instructions only.
And let us begin with white space.
Now, what should we do
with with white space?
Once again, I've used red ink to highlight
all the white space in the program.
And the easiest way to
deal with white space and
obviously the most sensible
way is to simply ignore it.
So as you process the source code
whenever you see a comment or
an empty line,
you simply toss away all this
all the contents the follow,
that follow in this specific line.
And you go on to translate
the remaining code.
So white space is simply ignored.
So what remains after we eliminate
eliminate the white space
is only instructions.
So the challenge is reduced to translating
programs that have pure instructions,
so to speak, and
these are this is a sequence or
a stream of A-instructions and
C-instructions.
And in order to translate them,
we have to know how to translate
these instructions into binary code.
And that's exactly what we
are going to do in the next unit.
But before we introduce the next unit,
I'd like to give you an overall picture
of where we're heading from here onward.
Well here's the, here's the plan.
Since we decided to defer the treatment
of symbols to a later stage,
we'll begin by writing a basic assembler
that can deal with programs
that contain no symbols.
This will be done in the next unit.
In the subsequent unit, we are going
to develop the ability to represent,
handle, and use symbols.
And finally, using this ability, we
are going to return to the basic assembler
that we wrote before and morph it or
extend it into a general purpose assembler
that can translate any given program,
any given program written in Hack
assembly code into binary code.
This is the plan.
So beginning with the next unit,
we're going to talk about how
to translate instructions.